<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>GDPRhub</sitename>
    <dbname>gdprwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://gdprhub.eu/index.php?title=Welcome_to_GDPRhub</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.6</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">GDPRhub</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">GDPRhub talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>ADA (Lithuania)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>265</id>
    <revision>
      <id>12566</id>
      <parentid>12564</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-12-01T14:38:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mh</username>
        <id>391</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>12566</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2132" sha1="4wfz66o4o8dwwyrvdjzu0dqy1p6yleo" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAbox
|logo           = [[File:logoLT.png|center|250px]] &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|geo            = Lithuania
|name           = Valstybinė duomenų apsaugos inspekcija
|abbreviation   = ADA  &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|head           = Raimondas Andrijauskas &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|deputy         = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|address        = A. Juozapaviciaus str. 6 &lt;br&gt; LT-09310 Vilnius &lt;br&gt; Lithuania &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|webpage        = https://www.ada.lt &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|email          = ada@ada.lt &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|phone          = +370-5-2791445 &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|twitter        = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL; Only twitter-handle --&gt;
|procedural law = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|decision db    = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|head count     = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|budget         = &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
|wikidata       = Q56056071 &lt;!-- OPTIONAL --&gt;
}}

The Data Protection Office (''Valstybinė duomenų apsaugos inspekcija'') is the national Data Protection Authority for Lithuania. It resides in Vilnius and is in charge of enforcing GDPR in Lithuania.

==Structure==
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

==Procedural Information==

===Applicable Procedural Law===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

===Complaints Procedure under Art 77 GDPR===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

===''Ex Officio'' Procedures under Art 57 GDPR===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

===Appeals===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

==Practical Information==

=== Filing with the DPA ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Known Problems ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Filing an Appeal ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

==Decision Database==
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

==Statistics==

=== Funding ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Personal ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Caseload ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Fines ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

=== Annual Reports ===
''You can help us by filling in this section!''

{{DataProtectionAuthorities}}</text>
      <sha1>4wfz66o4o8dwwyrvdjzu0dqy1p6yleo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ADA - N/A</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>11848</id>
      <parentid>11421</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-10-22T16:04:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SR</username>
        <id>215</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>11848</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8077" sha1="q45mjgvsvfppqwizzlch8gz2rlvwjp3" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAdecisionBOX

|Jurisdiction=Lithuania
|DPA-BG-Color=background-color:#ffffff;
|DPAlogo=LogoLT.png
|DPA_Abbrevation=ADA
|DPA_With_Country=ADA (Lithuania)

|Case_Number_Name=
|ECLI=

|Original_Source_Name_1=Lithuanian DPA (VDAI) Press release
|Original_Source_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/lt/news/view_item/id.143
|Original_Source_Language_1=Lithuanian
|Original_Source_Language__Code_1=LT

|Type=Complaint
|Outcome=Upheld
|Date_Decided=
|Date_Published=
|Year=2020
|Fine=15000
|Currency=EUR

|GDPR_Article_1=Article 5(1)(d) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_1=Article 5 GDPR#1d
|GDPR_Article_2=Article 5(1)(f) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_2=Article 5 GDPR#1f



|Party_Name_1=Vilnius City Municipality Administration
|Party_Link_1=https://vilnius.lt/en/
|Party_Name_2=
|Party_Link_2=
|Party_Name_3=
|Party_Link_3=
|Party_Name_4=
|Party_Link_4=
|Party_Name_5=
|Party_Link_5=

|Appeal_To_Body=
|Appeal_To_Case_Number_Name=
|Appeal_To_Status=Unknown
|Appeal_To_Link=

|Initial_Contributor=Linas Mockevicius
|
}}

Lithuanian DPA imposes a fine of EUR 15.000,00 for a failure to implement sufficient technical and organizational measures with regards to education procedures of an adopted child.

==English Summary==

===Facts===
An applicant applied to the Vilnius City Administration (hereinafter - the Administration) with regards to the education of an adopted child. However, under the agreement concluded between the Administration and the State Registry, the information in the IT system was automatically updated once a month according to the data available in the State Registry. Due to this, the applicant's email was automatically replaced by the email of a biological father of the adopted child. 

===Dispute===
Did the Administration fulfill its obligations under the GDPR with regards to the unilateral changes of applicant's email?

===Holding===
The DPA held that the Administration did not have a right under the GDPR to unilaterally change the applicant's email address according to the data provided in the State Registry. Furthermore, there are no grounds to believe that the information received from the State Registry belongs to the applicant, since the data was updated based on the child's data rather than the applicant's data in the State Registry. Hence, having processed personal data of the biological father of the child, the Administration performed a breach of principles of accuracy as well as integrity and confidentiality established in the Para 1 d and f of the Article 5 of the GDPR respectively. 

==Comment==
An interesting idea from the DPA is that one's personal contact information such as email address, notwithstanding such information is provided in the State Registry, should be only changed by the data subject and the data controller should refrain itself from unilaterally changing, based on information in the public registries. 
Furthermore, it is worth mentioning that last year the Administration was imposed an order for exactly same breach of GDPR, nevertheless, no actions were taken in spite of this. This was one of the reasons why such fine was imposed. 
The decision could be appealed to the court. 

==Further Resources==
''Share blogs or news articles here!''

==English Machine Translation of the Decision==
The decision below is a machine translation of the Lithuanian original. Please refer to the Lithuanian original for more details.

&lt;pre&gt;
The State Data Protection Inspectorate punished the Vilnius City Municipality Administration for violations of the General Data Protection Regulation. 15 thousand. A fine of EUR 1 million was imposed for incorrect processing of personal data of the adopted child's parents.

The State Data Protection Inspectorate (hereinafter - SDPI) allocated LTL 15,000 to the Vilnius City Municipality Administration (hereinafter - the municipal administration) for violations of the General Data Protection Regulation (hereinafter - BDAR). an administrative fine of EUR. The fine is imposed for violations of Article 5 (1) (d) and (f) of the BDAR - failure to implement appropriate technical and organizational measures, thus not ensuring the accuracy of the personal data processed, processing personal data of the adopted child's parents.

After conducting an investigation, the SDPI found that the applicant had submitted his data in the Centralized Application and Population Information System (hereinafter - IS) of the municipal administration when filling in the application for the adoption of the adopted child, however, according to the municipal administration agreement with the State Enterprise Register Center. The IS was updated once a month, after the automatic updating of the IS data the contact details of the applicant were updated and changed to the contact details (e-mail address) of one of the child's biological parents in the Population Register of the Republic of Lithuania (hereinafter - the Population Register).

When processing personal data, the municipal administration must follow the principle of accuracy, which stipulates that personal data must be accurate and, if necessary, kept up to date, and all reasonable measures must be taken to ensure that personal data that are inaccurate are deleted without delay. (Article 5 (1) (d) BDAR) and the principle of integrity and confidentiality, which stipulates that personal data must be processed in such a way as to ensure adequate security of personal data by appropriate technical or organizational means, including protection against unauthorized processing. authorization or unlawful processing of data and against unintentional loss, destruction or damage (Article 5 (1) (f) BDAR).

In the decision imposing a fine on the municipal administration, the SDPI stated that in a specific case, personal contact details such as e-mail address, whether or not they exist, and if listed in the Population Register, can be changed at any time and only the data subject should to change them, and not the data controller to update the data arbitrarily on the basis of the information in the State Enterprise Center of Registers. Moreover, in this case there was no reason to conclude that after updating the data from the Population Register the contact details of the applicant were obtained, as the data were updated not according to the applicant's data specified in the State Enterprise Register Center, but according to the child's data. child and the applicant. Thus, the municipal administration did not implement appropriate organizational and technical measures by handling the e-mail address of a third party (one of the child's biological parents) as the contact details of the applicant, thus failing to ensure the accuracy of the personal data processed and violating Article 5 (1) (d) and (f).

When deciding on the amount of the administrative fine, the SDPI assessed all the circumstances relevant to the application of liability to the municipal administration, such as:
- Although in the present case the breach committed by the municipal administration concerns only individuals (applicants), it is not in principle an accident and would have occurred to any person in the same circumstances due to improper technical and organizational measures of the municipal administration in processing personal data;
- That data on the adoption of the child, which is highly sensitive data, and his further education have been disclosed;
- That the infringement was committed negligently;
- That the municipal administration committed the violation repeatedly, due to a similar violation (improper implementation of organizational and technical measures without ensuring the principle of accuracy of personal data when processing the adopted child's personal data in the IS of the Municipal Administration) in 2019. was reprimanded.

The amount of the fine for the municipal administration also took into account the amount of the institution's budget for the current year and other gross annual revenues received in the previous year.

This decision of VDAI is not valid and can be appealed to a court.
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
      <sha1>q45mjgvsvfppqwizzlch8gz2rlvwjp3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ADA - Quarantine App ("Karantinas")</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3186</id>
    <revision>
      <id>13819</id>
      <parentid>13818</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-03-01T14:26:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mh</username>
        <id>391</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>13819</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11646" sha1="ebsh21w2hy0om89cnw2iukkt5rzacy6" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAdecisionBOX

|Jurisdiction=Lithuania
|DPA-BG-Color=background-color:#ffffff;
|DPAlogo=LogoLT.png
|DPA_Abbrevation=ADA
|DPA_With_Country=ADA (Lithuania)

|Case_Number_Name=Quarantine App ("Karantinas")
|ECLI=

|Original_Source_Name_1=Valstybinė duomenų apsaugos inspekcija
|Original_Source_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/lt/naujienos/skirta-bauda-del-bendrojo-duomenu-apsaugos-reglamento-pazeidimu-programeleje-karantinas
|Original_Source_Language_1=Lithuanian
|Original_Source_Language__Code_1=LT

|Type=Investigation
|Outcome=Violation Found
|Date_Decided=
|Date_Published=26.02.2021
|Year=
|Fine=15000
|Currency=EUR

|GDPR_Article_1=Article 5 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_1=Article 5 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_2=Article 5(1)(a) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_2=Article 5 GDPR#1a
|GDPR_Article_3=Article 5(1)(f) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_3=Article 5 GDPR#1f
|GDPR_Article_4=Article 13 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_4=Article 13 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_5=Article 24 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_5=Article 24 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_6=Article 32 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_6=Article 32 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_7=Article 35 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_7=Article 35 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_8=Article 58(2)(f) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_8=Article 58 GDPR#2f



|Party_Name_1=Nacionaliniam visuomenės sveikatos centrui (NVSC)
|Party_Link_1=https://nvsc.lrv.lt/
|Party_Name_2=UAB „IT sprendimai sėkmei“ (Company)
|Party_Link_2=
|Party_Name_3=
|Party_Link_3=
|Party_Name_4=
|Party_Link_4=
|Party_Name_5=
|Party_Link_5=

|Appeal_To_Body=
|Appeal_To_Case_Number_Name=
|Appeal_To_Status=
|Appeal_To_Link=

|Initial_Contributor=n/a
|
}}

The Lithuanian DPA (VDAI) imposed two fines after investigating the Quarantine App launched by the National Center for Public Health in cooperation with UAB IT Solutions Success. The National Center for Public Health was fined €12,000 for breaching Articles 5, 13, 24, 32, 35 and 58(2)(f) GDPR. UAB IT Solutions Success was fined €3,000 for violating Articles 5, 13, 24, 32 and 35 GDPR. 

==English Summary==

===Facts===
The Lithuanian DPA (VDAI) launched an investigation into the Lithuanian Quarantine App ("Karantinas") in May 2020 after information in the media that there potentially was unlawful processing of personal data involved. This App was launched by the National Center for Public Health (Nacionaliniam visuomenės sveikatos centrui) and developed by UAB IT Solutions Success (UAB „IT sprendimai sėkmei“). 

The App was suspended after preliminary findings which triggered the investigation process. The DPA ordered UAB IT Solutions Success to suspend the processing of personal data. However, UAB IT deleted this data instead. 

In the investigation, the DPA found that the personal data of 677 individuals were collected in April 2020. This generally included personal data such as identification number, latitude and longitude coordinates, country, city, municipality, postal code, street name, house number, name, surname, personal code, telephone number, address, 2nd address, whether the place of residence is declared in Lithuania and other information. The processing was conducted in Lithuania, other EU/EEA States, as well as third countries (non-EU such as India and the US).

===Dispute===
Was the Lithuanian Quarantine App in violation of the GDPR?

===Holding===
The Lithuanian DPA first established that the National Center for Public Health (Nacionaliniam visuomenės sveikatos centrui) and the Company responsible for developing the App,  UAB IT Solutions Success (UAB „IT sprendimai sėkmei“), were joint controllers. 

The DPA discovered from its investigation that a Data Protection Impact Assessment had to be done prior to processing in line with Article 35 GDPR. The App concerned processed personal data using new technology as well as a systematic monitoring of data subjects in self-isolation. The App also aimed to process large datasets (data subjects throughout Lithuania and abroad). The processing was intended to be continuous and vulnerable data subjects were concerned. 

The DPA found that the National Center for Public Health violated Article 24 and 32 GDPR on the implementation of organisational measures, as well as the principle of integrity and confidentiality found in Article 5(1)(f) GDPR.

The DPA found that both the National Center for Public Health and UAB IT Solutions Success violated the principle of lawfulness Article 5(1)(a) GDPR as they failed to prove that they had a legal basis for processing. The principle of transparency was also infringed (Article 5(1)(a)) . Finally, as neither entities recognised that they were data controllers, the accountability principle was not met (violation of Article 5(2)). 

In summary, the DPA found that the National Center for Public Health breached Articles 5, 13, 24, 32, 35 and 58 (2)(f) GDPR and imposed a fine of €12,000 on the public body. In turn, the DPA found that UAB IT Solutions Success violated Articles 5, 13, 24, 32 and 35 GDPR and imposed a fine of €3,000.

The fines reached this level as the National Center for Public Health and UAB IT Solutions Success processed personal data without a legal basis in an intentional way, systematically, without technical and organisational measures. The DPA also took into consideration that this concerned special categories of personal data. Finally, in addition, UAB IT Solutions Success did not comply with the DPA's request to suspend the processing and instead, deleted the personal data collected.

==Comment==
The DPA's decision can be appealed within 1 month from the date of the decision

==Further Resources==
''Share blogs or news articles here!''

==English Machine Translation of the Decision==
The decision below is a machine translation of the Lithuanian original. Please refer to the Lithuanian original for more details.

&lt;pre&gt;
2020 May. after the temporary suspension of the use of the Quarantine app, in 2021. February. Following an investigation carried out by the State Data Protection Inspectorate (SDPI), fines were imposed on the National Center for Public Health (NVSC) and UAB IT Solutions Success (the Company), which developed the app, for violations of the General Data Protection Regulation (BDAR).

NVSC 12 thousand. a fine has been imposed for infringements of Articles 5, 13, 24, 32, 35 and 58 (2) (f) of the BDAR. The company has 3 thousand. a fine was imposed for the established violations of Articles 5, 13, 24, 32 and 35 of the BDAR.

2020 In the spring of 2006, the SDPI started monitoring activities in response to information in the media about the possible improper processing of personal data by the Quarantine program. After evaluating the initial information, it was decided to open an investigation and temporarily suspend the processing of personal data by the app.

The study found that when the app became operational in 2020, in April data from 677 individuals were collected. Not all personal data was collected to the same extent, but the app provides processing of personal data such as identification number, latitude and longitude coordinates, country, city, municipality, postal code, street name, house number, name, surname, personal code, telephone number, address, 2nd address, whether the place of residence is declared in Lithuania and other information. According to the submitted data, it was established that the processing of the app data was performed not only in the territory of Lithuania, but also in Europe (Estonia, Switzerland, etc.) and abroad (India, USA, etc.).

After conducting an investigation, the SDPI found that both NVSC and the Company are joint data controllers, although both organizations denied such status.

When deciding on the imposition and amount of the administrative fine, VDAI took into account the fact that NVSC and the Company processed personal data intentionally, to a large extent, illegally, systematically, without providing technical and organizational means to prove compliance with BDAR requirements. , special categories of personal data were processed. In addition, the Company did not comply with the instruction given to it by VDAI to suspend the processing of personal data collected with the help of the app and deleted part of the personal data.

The decision of the SDPI may be appealed to a court within one month from the date of its service in accordance with the procedure established by legal acts.

 

More research information

Data Protection Impact Assessment (DPA). Following an investigation, the SDPI found that a data protection impact assessment (PDAV) had to be carried out in order to process the data. Article 35 (1) of the BDAR provides that in cases where the nature of the processing, in particular the use of new technologies, and the nature, scope, context and purposes of the processing, the rights and freedoms of natural persons may be seriously jeopardized, , performs PDAV of the planned data processing operations before starting the data processing.

The processing of personal data by the app is considered as processing using a new technology, as well as as a systematic monitoring, as in this case the processing is carried out by data subjects using the app for self-isolation monitoring and control. Also, with the help of the app it was planned to process a large number of personal data of data subjects in the whole territory of Lithuania and abroad. In addition, according to the information collected during the VDAI investigation, it can be concluded that the processing of personal data was planned to be carried out on a continuous basis. Persons identified as vulnerable, ie patients, children, the elderly, etc., were treated. personal data, including but not limited to health data.

Among other things, in the opinion of VDAI, NVSC managed state information resources by performing the function of prevention and control of communicable diseases and processing personal data collected by the app, and violated the requirements of Articles 24 and 32 of the BDAR. on the implementation of appropriate organizational measures and the principle of integrity and confidentiality provided for in Article 5 (1) (f) BDAR (personal data must be processed in such a way as to ensure adequate security of personal data by appropriate technical or organizational measures, accidental loss, destruction or damage).

Violated principles. Taking into account that NVSC and the Company have not proved the lawfulness of the processing of personal data carried out by the app, VDAI established a violation of the principle of lawfulness provided for in Article 5 (1) of the BDAR. As neither NVSC nor the Company acknowledged that they were data controllers during the inspection, both denied their liability as data controllers and accordingly did not implement the accountability principle set out in Article 5 (2) of the BDAR. The gadget's privacy policy also violated the principle of transparency by providing incorrect information about data controllers and processors.

Failure to comply with the order. During the inspection of personal data processed by the app, it was important for VDAI to assess the actual scope and nature of personal data processing, therefore VDAI instructed the Company to temporarily suspend the processing of personal data through the app, but the Company deleted the data. By deleting the personal data processed by the app, the company did not properly implement the instruction given to it by VDAI and thus violated Article 58 (2) (f) of the BDAR. It should be noted that such non-compliance with the instructions of VDAI incurs the Company's liability provided for in Article 83 (5) (e) of the BDAR. 
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ebsh21w2hy0om89cnw2iukkt5rzacy6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ADA - VĮ Registrų centras</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3209</id>
    <revision>
      <id>13937</id>
      <parentid>13936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-03-10T07:06:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mh</username>
        <id>391</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* English Machine Translation of the Decision */</comment>
      <origin>13937</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8209" sha1="2wda4pyrifsfz363ad8co7d0n7w2zpa" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAdecisionBOX

|Jurisdiction=Lithuania
|DPA-BG-Color=background-color:#ffffff;
|DPAlogo=LogoLT.png
|DPA_Abbrevation=ADA
|DPA_With_Country=ADA (Lithuania)

|Case_Number_Name=VĮ Registrų centras
|ECLI=

|Original_Source_Name_1=Valstybinė duomenų apsaugos inspekcija 
|Original_Source_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/lt/naujienos/skirta-bauda-del-bendrojo-duomenu-apsaugos-reglamento-pazeidimu-registru-centre
|Original_Source_Language_1=Lithuanian
|Original_Source_Language__Code_1=LT

|Type=Investigation
|Outcome=Violation Found
|Date_Decided=
|Date_Published=02.03.2021
|Year=
|Fine=15000
|Currency=EUR

|GDPR_Article_1=Article 32(1)(b) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_1=Article 32 GDPR#1b
|GDPR_Article_2=Article 32(1)(c) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_2=Article 32 GDPR#1c
|GDPR_Article_3=Article 83(2)(a) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_3=Article 83 GDPR#2a
|GDPR_Article_4=Article 83(2)(d) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_4=Article 83 GDPR#2d
|GDPR_Article_5=Article 83(2)(g) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_5=Article 83 GDPR#2g



|Party_Name_1=VĮ Registrų centras
|Party_Link_1=https://www.registrucentras.lt/
|Party_Name_2=
|Party_Link_2=
|Party_Name_3=
|Party_Link_3=
|Party_Name_4=
|Party_Link_4=
|Party_Name_5=
|Party_Link_5=

|Appeal_To_Body=
|Appeal_To_Case_Number_Name=
|Appeal_To_Status=Unknown
|Appeal_To_Link=

|Initial_Contributor=n/a
|
}}

The Lithuanian State Data Protection Inspectorate (VDAI) imposed a fine of €15,000 on the Center of Registers (VĮ Registrų centras) for improper implementation of technical and organizational data security measures. 

==English Summary==

===Facts===
Starting in July 2020, the VDAI was investigating the incident of a data breach in the systems maintained by the State Enterprise Center of Registers. The data affected by the data breach was stored in:
   Electronic health services and collaboration infrastructure information system;
   Real estate register;
   Real estate cadastre;
   Register of Legal Entities;
   Population Register of the Republic of Lithuania;
   Register of seizure deeds;
   Mortgage Register of the Republic of Lithuania;
   Register of wills;
   Register of marriage contracts;
   Register of credentials;
   Register of incapacitated and restricted persons;
   Register of contracts;
   Information system for participants of legal entities;
   Bailiffs information system;
   License information system;
   Money Restriction Information System;
   Legal aid services information system;
   Registration service information system;
   Electronic signature and timestamp service;
   Register center document management system;
   Personnel administration system of the Register Center;
   Accounting software of the Register Center.

===Dispute===
===Holding===
The fine of 15000 EUR was imposed for infringements of Article 32(1) (b) and (c) of the BDAR, ie failure to ensure the integrity, availability and resilience of data processing systems and services as well as failure to restore the conditions and access to personal data in the event of a physical or technical incident within the legal deadline. 

In determining the amount of the administrative fine, the VDAI took into account the factors mitigating the violation committed by the Center of Registers listed in Article 83(2) (b), (c), (e), (f) and (h) GDPR, i. e. the absence of intent, the efforts made to restore the damaged data, the absence of facts about the material damage suffered by the data subjects, the close cooperation with the VDAI and the absence of previous violations of a similar nature. The VDAI also took into account that the Center of Registers, when implementing security measures, is dependent on both the data controller, the Ministry of Health of the Republic of Lithuania, and other institutions dealing with the consolidation of state IT resources, and ruled that the proposed fine was a proportionate sanction to ensure future compliance with the provisions of the GDPR.

==Comment==
''Share your comments here!''

==Further Resources==
''Share blogs or news articles here!''

==English Machine Translation of the Decision==
The decision below is a machine translation of the Lithuanian original. Please refer to the Lithuanian original for more details.

&lt;pre&gt;
After 2020 July 20 The State Data Protection Inspectorate (SDPI), having conducted an investigation under the General Data Protection Regulation (BDAR), in 2021. February. imposed a fine for improper implementation of technical and organizational data security measures.

SE Register Center 15 thousand. A fine of EUR 1 million was imposed for infringements of Article 32 (1) (b) and (c) of the BDAR, ie failure to ensure the integrity, availability and resilience of data processing systems and services and failure to restore access to personal data in the event of a physical or technical incident within the legal deadline.

Registers and state information systems maintained by the State Enterprise Center of Registers that were affected during the personal data security breach:

    Electronic health services and collaboration infrastructure information system;
    Real estate register;
    Real estate cadastre;
    Register of Legal Entities;
    Population Register of the Republic of Lithuania;
    Register of seizure deeds;
    Mortgage Register of the Republic of Lithuania;
    Register of wills;
    Register of marriage contracts;
    Register of credentials;
    Register of incapacitated and restricted persons;
    Register of contracts;
    Information system for participants of legal entities;
    Bailiffs information system;
    License information system;
    Money Restriction Information System;
    Legal aid services information system;
    Registration service information system;
    Electronic signature and timestamp service;
    Register center document management system;
    Personnel administration system of the Register Center;
    Accounting software of the Register Center.

Considering that the State Enterprise Center of Registers is the data processor and / or data controller of these 22 registers and information systems, taking into account the level of development of technical possibilities, implementation costs and the nature, scope, context and objectives of data processing, as well as data processing costs. various risks and seriousness risks to the rights and freedoms of natural persons without appropriate technical and organizational measures to ensure a level of security commensurate with the risks, in breach of Article 32 (1) (b) and (c) BDAR and Article 83 (2) (a), (d) and The factors listed in points (g) (related to the nature, gravity, duration and scope of the data), which are to be recognized as aggravating the infringement of the State Enterprise Center of Registers, have been decided to impose an administrative fine on the State Enterprise Center of Registers.

Pursuant to the Law on the Legal Protection of Personal Data, an authority or body that violates the provisions of Article 83 (4) (a), (b) and (c) of the BDAR has the right to impose an administrative fine of up to 0.5 per cent of the authority or body's current year's budget and other gross annual income, but not more than thirty thousand euros.

In determining the amount of the administrative fine, VDAI took into account the mitigating factors listed in Article 83 (2) (b), (c), (e), (f) and (h) of the BDAR, ie lack of intent, efforts to close cooperation with the SDPI and the absence of previous violations of a similar nature. The SDPI also took into account that the State Enterprise Center of Registers, when implementing security measures, is dependent both on the data controller, the Ministry of Health of the Republic of Lithuania, and other institutions dealing with consolidation of state IT resources, and decided that the fine is a proportionate measure to to ensure compliance with the provisions of the BDAR in the future.

VDAI points out that ensuring the security of personal data is not only the duty of the data controller, but also the direct responsibility of the data processor provided for in Article 32 of the BDAR. The controller is directly liable for non-compliance or improper performance of this obligation. 
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
      <sha1>2wda4pyrifsfz363ad8co7d0n7w2zpa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ADA (Lithuania) - UAB VS FITNESS</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3610</id>
    <revision>
      <id>19319</id>
      <parentid>19318</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-09-09T10:09:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FA</username>
        <id>619</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>19319</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="54211" sha1="inn5i499l3tw4q4539pjs7d2zur0glv" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAdecisionBOX

|Jurisdiction=Lithuania
|DPA-BG-Color=background-color:#ffffff;
|DPAlogo=LogoLT.png
|DPA_Abbrevation=ADA (Lithuania)
|DPA_With_Country=ADA (Lithuania)

|Case_Number_Name=n/a
|ECLI=n/a

|Original_Source_Name_1=	Valstybinė duomenų apsaugos inspekcija
|Original_Source_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/lt/naujienos/sporto-klubui-skirta-bauda-uz-bendrojo-duomenu-apsaugos-reglamento-pazeidimus-tvarkant-klientu-ir-darbuotoju-pirstu-atspaudus
|Original_Source_Language_1=Lithuanian
|Original_Source_Language__Code_1=LT

|Type=Investigation
|Outcome=Violation Found
|Date_Decided=21.06.2021
|Date_Published=
|Year=2021
|Fine=20,000
|Currency=

|GDPR_Article_1=Article 5(1)(c) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_1=Article 5 GDPR#1c
|GDPR_Article_2=Article 5(1)(a) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_2=Article 5 GDPR#1a
|GDPR_Article_3=Article 9(1) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_3=Article 9 GDPR#1
|GDPR_Article_4=Article 13(1) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_4=Article 13 GDPR#1
|GDPR_Article_5=Article 13(2) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_5=Article 13 GDPR#2
|GDPR_Article_6=Article 30 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_6=Article 30 GDPR
|GDPR_Article_7=Article 35(1) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_7=Article 35 GDPR#1



|Party_Name_1=UAB VS FITNESS
|Party_Link_1=
|Party_Name_2=
|Party_Link_2=
|Party_Name_3=
|Party_Link_3=
|Party_Name_4=
|Party_Link_4=
|Party_Name_5=
|Party_Link_5=

|Appeal_To_Body=
|Appeal_To_Case_Number_Name=
|Appeal_To_Status=Unknown
|Appeal_To_Link=

|Initial_Contributor=n/a
|
}}

The Lithuanian DPA fined a sports club approximately €20,000 for processing the biometric data of its customers and employees in violation of Articles 9(1), 13(1) and (2), 30, and 35(1) GDPR.

== English Summary ==

=== Facts ===
The Lithuanian DPA ('VDAI') received a complaint stating that in order to use the services of a sports club (UAB VS FITNESS), fingerprint scanning is required. It then initiated an own volition investigation of a possible breach of the GDPR.  

=== Holding ===
The VDAI found that the sports club had violated the following GDPR provisions:  

* It violated Article 9(1) GDPR by processing the biometric data of customers, which is special category data. The sports club had attempted to rely on the consent exception, outlined at Article 9(2), that special category data may be processed where the data subject provides their consent. However, the VDAI found that consent collected from customers did not satisfy the requirements for valid consent established in the GDPR. In particular, since consent to the biometric system was not voluntary, it was not freely given;
* The processing of employees' fingerprints was also in breach of Article 9(1) GDPR, as the club had again attempted to rely on consent as a basis for processing. The VDAI highlighted that employee consent is generally considered invalid due to the power imbalance with an employer. Moreover, the club did not specify the purpose and legal basis of the processing of employee data, nor had it demonstrated the necessity and proportionality of this processing, in violation of Article 5(1)(c) GDPR;
* It violated Article 13(1) and (1) GDPR, and Article 5(1) GDPR by failing to adequately inform data subject's about the processing of their data;
* It failed to perform an assessment of the impact of the processing of biometric data, in violation of Article 35(1) GDPR;
* It did not manage a record of its processing activities, in violation of Article 30 GDPR.

It thus issued a fine of €20,000. In determining the fine, the VDAI took into account:      

* The processing of special categories of personal data;     
* That Improper exercise of data subject's right to be informed falls into a category of more serious infringements under Article 83(5) GDPR;     
* That the club had previously been instructed on how to lawfully process biometric data at another sports club it owned, for example by making the processing of biometric data voluntary, offering an equivalent, optional alternative to identification without the use of fingerprints, and providing customers the possibility to cancel the use of fingerprints at any time should be regulated. In view of these circumstances, the VDIA considered the illegal processing of customers' personal data to be an intentional violation.      
* The club's turnover of the previous and current year, as well as circumstances indicated by the club that the activities of sports clubs were severely restricted due to the coronavirus pandemic this year.      

== Comment ==
== Further Resources ==
''Share blogs or news articles here!''

== English Machine Translation of the Decision ==
The decision below is a machine translation of the Lithuanian original. Please refer to the Lithuanian original for more details.

&lt;pre&gt;

    
        
                        

    
    



    
        
            
                
                                        
                        Navigation
                        Navigation
                        
                        
                        
                    
                                    
                
                    
                                        

                                                    My government
                                                BUT A
                
                
                    
                                                        
            en
            [[language]]
        
    
                
            

            
                
                    
                    Site map
                
                                                    
            en
            [[language]]
        
    
                
                    [[disabilities]]
                
            

            
                                                                    
                                                                        
                                Prime Minister
                            
                                                                                                
                                Government Office
                            
                                                                                                
                                Ministries
                            
                                                                                                
                                Institutions
                            
                                                                                                
                                E. citizen
                            
                                                                                                            
                                
                
                    For the disabled
                
            

            
        
    



    
        
            
                
            
            
                State Data Protection Inspectorate
            
        
        
    



            
            
        
    
    

    

    
                
            
            
            
        
        Navigation
    
    
        

        
            navbar
                        
        

        
            to the start
            News subscription
            
        
        
            
                

                                                                    
                        
                            
                                News
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Structure and contacts
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Structure
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Contacts
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    How to find us
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Legal information
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Legislation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Draft legislation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Legal practice
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Research and analysis
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Violations of legislation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Monitoring of legal regulation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Areas of activity
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Preventive inspections
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Prior consultation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Audits
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Complaints handling
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        
                                                
                                                
                                                    Data security breaches
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    International cooperation
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Informing the public
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Corruption prevention
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Administrative information
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Regulations
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Planning documents
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Protection of whistleblowers
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Wage
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Incentives and awards
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Procurement
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Budget implementation report sets
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Sets of financial statements
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Supervision of economic operators
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Official passenger cars
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Activity reports
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Electronic and administrative services
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Links
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                ADSP and DAP
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Data breach notification
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Data Protection Officer
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Protection of personal data
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                useful information
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        
                                                
                                                
                                                    Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Recommendations, guidelines, etc.
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    COVID-19 and BDAR
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Summaries of inspection results
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    VDAI decisions (fines, instructions, etc.)
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Court decisions (according to VDAI complaints)
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    2018 data protection reform
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Public consultation before BDAR
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    SolPriPa 2 WORK project
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    SOLPriPa PROJECT
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Projects
                                                
                                                
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                                                                                    
                                                        
                                                            
                                                            
                                                                EU twinning project no. UA / 47b "Strengthening the institutional capacity of the High Commissioner for Human Rights of the Parliament of Ukraine to protect human rights and freedoms in line with European best practice"
                                                            
                                                            
                                                        
                                                                                                                                                                    
                                                        
                                                            
                                                            
                                                                Improving the qualification of civil servants and employees of the State Data Protection Inspectorate
                                                            
                                                            
                                                        
                                                                                                                                                                    
                                                        
                                                            
                                                            
                                                                Information systems interconnection and modernization project
                                                            
                                                            
                                                        
                                                                                                                                                                    
                                                        
                                                            
                                                            
                                                                Project “Increasing the cooperation between the State Data Protection Inspectorate and the Lithuanian Librarians' Association in implementing the personal data protection policy”
                                                            
                                                            
                                                        
                                                                                                        
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    For children and young people
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Open data
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        
                                                
                                                
                                                    Surveys
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        
                                                
                                                
                                                    Events archive
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        
                                                
                                                
                                                    Advertisements
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                    
            
        
        
            
        
    




        
        
            
                
                
                
            

            

                        

    A fine has been imposed on the sports club for breaches of the General Data Protection Regulation in the processing of fingerprints of customers and employees

    
    Home
            
                                                            News
                                                
            
                                                            A fine has been imposed on the sports club for breaches of the General Data Protection Regulation in the processing of fingerprints of customers and employees
                                                
    

    
        Print
        
    

    

    
        
            
                
                    Data
                    2121 2021
                
                                    
                        Evaluation
                        

    
            11
    

                    
                            
                                

        
                                                
                                    
                            

                                                
        The State Data Protection Inspectorate (State Data Protection Inspectorate) conducted an investigation into the processing of biometric personal data in a sports club and allocated LTL 20,000 for identified violations of the General Data Protection Regulation (BDAR). Eur fine to UAB VS FITNESS. The fine is imposed for violations of Article 5 (1) (a) and (c), Article 9 (1), Article 13 (1) to (2), Article 30, Article 35 (1) of the BDAR, i.e. y. for processing biometric data without voluntary consent of data subjects, as well as failure to ensure other requirements for valid consent, improper implementation of data subjects' right to be informed about data processing, as well as found that the company did not conduct a data protection impact assessment .

The Personal Data Protection Supervisor conducted an investigation
After receiving a notification from a natural person stating that in order to use the services of a sports club belonging to the company, a fingerprint scan is necessary, there are no other alternative means of identification in the said sports club, carried out an inspection on its own initiative in accordance with the Law on Legal Protection of Personal Data. with a possible BDAR violation in the company’s processing of fingerprints.

Processing of customer biometric data
According to the BDAR, biometric data belong to special categories of data, the processing of which is prohibited by the general rule, except for the conditions provided for in Article 9 (2) of the BDAR. The company processed customer fingerprint models with the consent of the data subjects, i. y. on the basis set out in Article 9 (2) (a) BDAR. VDAI noted that if the controller relies on the data subject's consent as a condition for lawful processing, he should ensure that the data subject's consent complies with the conditions imposed on him (voluntary, specific, reasonable information, unambiguity, as well as provability and revocability). During the inspection, VDAI found that the consent given by the customers to process their fingerprint models is not voluntary, nor does it meet the other requirements for a valid consent, which led the VDAI to decide that the company is processing the binary codes of the customers' fingerprints illegally.

Processing of employee biometric data
In addition, the VDAI found that the company had illegally processed the fingerprints of employees. The SDPI noted that employee consent due to a power imbalance is generally not considered an appropriate condition for the processing of personal data. VDAI did not specify the purpose and legal basis of the processing of employees 'biometric data, did not carry out a data protection impact assessment, and did not demonstrate the necessity and proportionality of the processing of employees' fingerprints. The SDPI noted that data subjects have the right to be informed about the processing of their data. Following the inspection, VDAI found that the company did not provide the data subjects with all the information required by the BDAR.

Relevant circumstances in deciding the amount of the fine
When deciding on the imposition of an administrative fine, VDAI assessed all relevant circumstances. The VDAI took into account that the processing of special categories of data in the absence of an exception, in violation of Article 5 (1) (a) and (c) and Article 9 (1) of the BDAR, as well as improper exercise of data subjects' right to be informed the requirements of Article 83 (1) to (2) of the EC Treaty fall into the category of more serious infringements (Article 83 (5) BDAR).
Among other things, the company had previously been instructed to process biometric data at another sports club it owned. This confirmed that the company was aware of how the voluntary requirement for customers to consent to the processing of their biometric data had to be met, that an equivalent, optional alternative to identification in sports clubs (without the use of fingerprint binary codes) had to be offered. Also that the possibility for the customer to cancel the use of the fingerprint model at any time must be regulated.
In view of these circumstances, VDAI considered the illegal processing of customers' biometric data to be an intentional violation. VDAI also took into account other identified aggravating and mitigating factors of the company's liability. In deciding the amount of the fine, VDAI took into account the information provided by the company on the turnover of the previous and current year, as well as the circumstances indicated by the company that the activities of sports clubs were severely restricted due to the coronavirus pandemic this year.
This decision of VDAI has not entered into force and can be appealed to a court.








        

                                                    
                    Share
        
        
                            
                    
                
                                                    
                    
                
                                
        
    

    

    

                
        
            
        Also read
                                    Review of personal data protection supervision in Lithuania in 2020
                                                The State Data Protection Inspectorate invites the Chief Specialist of the IT department of the team to join
                                                A digital environment that benefits and is safe for children - The Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development has issued a recommendation
                                                The European Data Protection Board has announced report
                                                SURVEY OF EMPLOYERS on the protection of personal data and privacy in the context of employment relationships
                        


        

    
    
    


            

            
                Back
                
                
            
        

        
            
                
                    
                        L.Sapiegos st. 17, 10312 Vilnius (Entrance from the left), tel. (8 5) 271 28 04, (8 5) 279 1445, fax. (8 5) 261 9494, el. p. ada@ada.lt

Data on the State Data Protection Inspectorate are collected and stored in the Register of Legal Entities. Code 188607912

Consultation tel. (8 5) 212 7532, Monday to Thursday, 9 a.m. to 11 a.m. and 1pm to 3pm

                        © Government of the Republic of Lithuania
                    

                    

                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                                                                        
                                        
                                    
                                
                                
                                    
                                        
                                    
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
                            
            
        
    

        
            
                
                    Data
                    2121 2021
                
                                    
                        Evaluation
                        

    
            11
    

                    
                            
                                

        
                                                
                                    
                            

                                                
        The State Data Protection Inspectorate (State Data Protection Inspectorate) conducted an investigation into the processing of biometric personal data in a sports club and allocated LTL 20,000 for identified violations of the General Data Protection Regulation (BDAR). Eur fine to UAB VS FITNESS. The fine is imposed for violations of Article 5 (1) (a) and (c), Article 9 (1), Article 13 (1) to (2), Article 30, Article 35 (1) of the BDAR, i.e. y. for processing biometric data without voluntary consent of data subjects, as well as failure to ensure other requirements for valid consent, improper implementation of data subjects' right to be informed about data processing, as well as found that the company did not conduct a data protection impact assessment .

The Personal Data Protection Supervisor conducted an investigation
After receiving a notification from a natural person stating that in order to use the services of a sports club belonging to the company, a fingerprint scan is necessary, there are no other alternative means of identification in the said sports club, carried out an inspection on its own initiative in accordance with the Law on Legal Protection of Personal Data. with a possible BDAR violation in the company’s processing of fingerprints.

Processing of customer biometric data
According to the BDAR, biometric data belong to special categories of data, the processing of which is prohibited by the general rule, except for the conditions provided for in Article 9 (2) of the BDAR. The company processed customer fingerprint models with the consent of the data subjects, i. y. on the basis set out in Article 9 (2) (a) BDAR. VDAI noted that if the controller relies on the data subject's consent as a condition for lawful processing, he should ensure that the data subject's consent complies with the conditions imposed on him (voluntary, specific, reasonable information, unambiguity, as well as provability and revocability). During the inspection, VDAI found that the consent given by the customers to process their fingerprint models is not voluntary, nor does it meet the other requirements for a valid consent, which led the VDAI to decide that the company is processing the binary codes of the customers' fingerprints illegally.

Processing of employee biometric data
In addition, the VDAI found that the company had illegally processed the fingerprints of employees. The SDPI noted that employee consent due to a power imbalance is generally not considered an appropriate condition for the processing of personal data. VDAI did not specify the purpose and legal basis of the processing of employees 'biometric data, did not carry out a data protection impact assessment, and did not demonstrate the necessity and proportionality of the processing of employees' fingerprints. The SDPI noted that data subjects have the right to be informed about the processing of their data. Following the inspection, VDAI found that the company did not provide the data subjects with all the information required by the BDAR.

Relevant circumstances in deciding the amount of the fine
When deciding on the imposition of an administrative fine, VDAI assessed all relevant circumstances. The VDAI took into account that the processing of special categories of data in the absence of an exception, in violation of Article 5 (1) (a) and (c) and Article 9 (1) of the BDAR, as well as improper exercise of data subjects' right to be informed the requirements of Article 83 (1) to (2) of the EC Treaty fall into the category of more serious infringements (Article 83 (5) BDAR).
Among other things, the company had previously been instructed to process biometric data at another sports club it owned. This confirmed that the company was aware of how the voluntary requirement for customers to consent to the processing of their biometric data had to be met, that an equivalent, optional alternative to identification in sports clubs (without the use of fingerprint binary codes) had to be offered. Also that the possibility for the customer to cancel the use of the fingerprint model at any time must be regulated.
In view of these circumstances, VDAI considered the illegal processing of customers' biometric data to be an intentional violation. VDAI also took into account other identified aggravating and mitigating factors of the company's liability. In deciding the amount of the fine, VDAI took into account the information provided by the company on the turnover of the previous and current year, as well as the circumstances indicated by the company that the activities of sports clubs were severely restricted due to the coronavirus pandemic this year.
This decision of VDAI has not entered into force and can be appealed to a court.








        

                                                    
                    Share
        
        
                            
                    
                
                                                    
                    
                
                                
        
    

    
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
      <sha1>inn5i499l3tw4q4539pjs7d2zur0glv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ADA (Lithuania) - ADA vs. UAB Prime Leasing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4395</id>
    <revision>
      <id>21728</id>
      <parentid>21726</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-12-07T14:30:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FA</username>
        <id>619</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>21728</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="38284" sha1="32epwcpzmi27mjxeeoqwrqwmm042j2c" xml:space="preserve">{{DPAdecisionBOX

|Jurisdiction=Lithuania
|DPA-BG-Color=background-color:#ffffff;
|DPAlogo=LogoLT.png
|DPA_Abbrevation=ADA (Lithuania)
|DPA_With_Country=ADA (Lithuania)

|Case_Number_Name=ADA vs. UAB Prime Leasing
|ECLI=

|Original_Source_Name_1=DPA Website Press Releases
|Original_Source_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/en/news/car-rental-company-fined-for-data-breach-under-the-general-data-protection-regulation
|Original_Source_Language_1=Lithuanian
|Original_Source_Language__Code_1=LT

|Type=Investigation
|Outcome=Violation Found
|Date_Decided=29.11.2021
|Date_Published=01.12.2021
|Year=2021
|Fine=110
|Currency=EUR

|GDPR_Article_1=Article 32(1)(a) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_1=Article 32 GDPR#1a
|GDPR_Article_2=Article 32(1)(b) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_2=Article 32 GDPR#1b
|GDPR_Article_3=Article 32(1)(d) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_3=Article 32 GDPR#1d
|GDPR_Article_4=Article 83(2)(a) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_4=Article 83 GDPR#2a
|GDPR_Article_5=Article 83(2)(b) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_5=Article 83 GDPR#2b
|GDPR_Article_6=Article 83(2)(g) GDPR
|GDPR_Article_Link_6=Article 83 GDPR#2g



|Party_Name_1=ADA
|Party_Link_1=https://vdai.lrv.lt/
|Party_Name_2=UAB Prime Leasing
|Party_Link_2=https://citybee.lt/lt/
|Party_Name_3=
|Party_Link_3=
|Party_Name_4=
|Party_Link_4=
|Party_Name_5=
|Party_Link_5=

|Appeal_To_Body=
|Appeal_To_Case_Number_Name=
|Appeal_To_Status=Unknown
|Appeal_To_Link=

|Initial_Contributor=Giel Ritzen
|
}}

The Lithuanian DPA (ADA) imposed a fine of €110,000 on UAB Prime Leasing for a lack of organisational and technical measures to ensure security of processing under [[Article 32 GDPR#1a|Article 32(1)(a)]], [[Article 32 GDPR#1b|Article 32(1)(b)]], and [[Article 32 GDPR#1d|Article 32(1)(d) GDPR]], which led to a data breach.

== English Summary ==

=== Facts ===
The Controller is the operator of a platform for short-term car rental: “CityBee”. It was made aware by another company that provides cyber-security services, that CityBee’s customer data of 110,302 users was published on the website RaidForums.com. The controller notified the DPA, who conducted an investigation. 

The DPA found out that the personal data was retrieved from an unprotected database backup BACPAC file (DB file), and contained the following: name, address, telephone number, e-mail address, personal identification number, driving license number, type of payment card and the last four digits of the number, the expiration date of the payment card, and the user identifier (token) in Braintree (software for online payments). This DB file was created on 27 February 2018, and access to the file was suspended on 16 February 2021. Hence, the DPA concluded that the personal data breach existed for this entire period. 

The DPA found that a number of organisational and technical security measures were missing: there was no competent person responsible for security and risk management, no logs were kept of access and changes to the DB files, the DB file was stored unencrypted, the passwords in the DB file had a weak encryption (SHA-1) and easy to retrieve by persons with technical knowledge, and users could make passwords that did not comply with the requirements as set out in the company’s IT security policy. Lastly, the controller did not assess and manage the risks associated with the loss of the DB file, since it was not even aware of the existence of this DB in the first place (!).

=== Holding ===
The DPA considered the lack of organizational and technical measures and held that properly using basic security measures, such as authenticated access to the DB file only for staff members, encrypting the DB file and entrusting only authorised staff members with the encryption key, or proper monitoring of information resources, would have ensured confidentiality of the personal data. Hence, it considered [[Article 32 GDPR#1a|Article 32(1)(a)]], [[Article 32 GDPR#1b|Article 32(1)(b)]], [[Article 32 GDPR#1d|Article 32(1)(d) GDPR]] to be breached.  

Pursuant to [[Article 82 GDPR#2|Article 82(2) GDPR]], the DPA took several aggravating factors into account to determine the amount of the fine. First, it noted that a large number of data subjects were affected, and that it is unclear how many persons have had access to the DB file, and to which extend the data have, and will still be, exploited ([[Article 82 GDPR#2a|Article 82(2)(a)]]). Second, the personal data contained personal identification numbers ([[Article 82 GDPR#2g|Article 82(2)(g)]]), and these unique identifiers were not encrypted. Lastly, the DPA held that the absence of a risk assessment on processing of the DB file, and the controller’s assumption that its process was secure, was negligent [[Article 82 GDPR#2b|Article 82(2)(b)]].  

The DPA also considered several other factors, such as the cooperation of the controller with the DPA, the fact that no sanctions were previously imposed on the controller ([[Article 82 GDPR#2e|Article 82(2)(e)]]), or the fact that the controller reported the data breach within the time limits set out in [[Article 34 GDPR]] ([[Article 82 GDPR#2h|Article 82(2)(h)]]). However, these factors were not considered to be either aggravating or mitigating. 

== Comment ==
Although the factors were all listed, the DPA considered only circumstances that were aggravating factors when determining the amount of the fine, as opposed to any circumstances that could be a mitigating factor. It is unclear why these latter circumstances were not considered as such. Moreover, since the breached data also contained personal data of 344 residents from other EU Member States, the DPA took its decision in accordance with the supervisory authorities of the Ireland, Germany, Austria, Italy, Portugal, Estonia, Belgium, Denmark, the Netherlands, Spain, Latvia, Sweden, Luxembourg, France, Norway, Finland, Slovakia and Slovenia.  

== Further Resources ==
''Share blogs or news articles here!''

== English Machine Translation of the Decision ==
The decision below is a machine translation of the Lithuanian original. Please refer to the Lithuanian original for more details.

&lt;pre&gt;

    
        
                        

    
    



    
        
            
                
                                        
                        Navigation
                        Navigation
                        
                        
                        
                    
                                    
                
                    
                                        

                                                    My Government
                                                BETA
                
                
                    
                                        
            lt
            Language
        
                    
                
            

            
                
                    
                    Sitemap
                
                                    
            lt
            Language
        
                    
                
                     For persons with disabilities
                
            

            
                                                                    
                                                                        
                                Prime Minister
                            
                                                                                                                                            
                                Ministries
                            
                                                                                                
                                Agencies
                            
                                                                                                
                                E. citizen
                            
                                                                                                            
                                
                
                    For the disabled
                
            

            
        
    



    
        
            
                
            
            
                State Data Protection Inspectorate
            
        
        
    



            
            
        
    
    

    

    
                
            
            
            
        
        Meniu
    
    
        

        
                        
            Close
        

        
            Į pradžią
            Newsletter subscription
            
        
        
            
                

                                                                    
                        
                            
                                News
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Structure and Contacts
                            
                            
                                                            
                                    
                                        
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Administration chart
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    Contacts
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                            
                                                
                                                
                                                    How to find us?
                                                
                                                
                                                                                            
                                                                                
                                    
                                
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Links
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Services
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                International cooperation
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                SolPriPa PROJECT
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                SolPriPa 2 WORK project
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Legislation
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Annual Reports
                            
                            
                                                    
                                                                    
                        
                            
                                Decisions of the Inspectorate (fines, orders, etc.)
                            
                            
                                                    
                                    
            
        
        
            
        
    




        
        
            
                
                
                
            

            

                        

    Car rental company fined for data breach under the General Data Protection Regulation

    
    Home
            
                                                            News
                                                
            
                                                            Car rental company fined for data breach under the General Data Protection Regulation
                                                
    

    
        Print
        
    

    

    
        
            
                
                    Date
                    2021 12 01
                
                                    
                        Rating
                        

    
            1
    

                    
                            
                                

        
                                                
                                    
                            

                                                
        The Personal Data Protection Supervisory Authority, the State Data Protection Inspectorate (SDPI), imposed an administrative fine of EUR 110,000 on UAB Prime Leasing, the operator of the short-term car rental platform CityBee, by its decision taken on 29 November 2021. The SDPI carried out an investigation on its own initiative following information that appeared in the public domain in February 2021 regarding a possible company’s customers personal data breach (PDB). The company was fined for breach of Article 32(1)(a), (b), (d) of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), which governs the obligation to ensure the security of processing of personal data.

ORIGIN OF THE BREACH

The investigation of UAB Prime Leasing has been launched on the initiative of the SDPI following information received that the personal data of the company’s customers, including personal identification numbers, had been made public. During the investigation, the company submitted a report to the Supervisory Authority on the PDB in the company’s IT infrastructure in accordance with the procedure established by legal acts. According to the company, it became aware of the breach from another company providing cyber-security services, which informed it that the CityBee’s customer data was published in CSV files on the website RaidForums.com. The investigation revealed that the publicly disposed data was obtained from an unprotected database backup BACPAC file (DB file) with a creation date of 27 February 2018. It turned out that the exact date of suspension of the external access to the said file was 16 February 2021 11:15 am. In the absence of any factual evidence to suggest that the said file was not publicly accessible during that period, it was concluded that the PDB lasted from 27 February 2018 to 16 February 2021.

Given the established ongoing nature of the PDB, and taking into account the start of the application of the GDPR, the Supervisory Authority assessed during the investigation the obligations of the company under the GDPR, both with regard to the PDB and the requirements for ensuring the security of personal data.  

MAIN RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATION

The investigation revealed the following:


	The date of creation of the DB file containing the personal data based on which the company’s customer personal data set in the CSV file was created and made public was 27 February 2018.
	The data of 110,302 CityBee users were disclosed and made public.
	433 users who had provided their residential address in other countries of the European Union and/or the European Economic Area were identified. 
	The following sensitive personal data were stored in plain text in a DB file: name, address, telephone number, e-mail address, personal identification number, driving licence number, type of payment card and the last four digits of the card number, the date of expiration of the payment card and the user identifier (token) in Braintree.
	The company failed to ensure adequate personal data management and control:
	
		did not appoint a person with appropriate competence to be responsible for security and risk management;
		did not separate the duties and responsibilities in the field of IT development and maintenance from the duties and responsibilities in the field of cyber security;
		did not ensure access to the DB file logs to record and store entries, and did not ensure that actions performed on DB files were recorded, monitored and evaluated;
		the DB file was stored unencrypted, so that a person with technical knowledge could get full access to the data contained in the file after downloading it. The personal identification numbers in the DB file were also stored in plain text and unprotected by hashing or encryption algorithms;
		the passwords in the DB file were encrypted with the weak and relatively insecure hashing algorithm SHA-1 . It was easy for persons with technical knowledge to find out the real (unmasked by means of hash) values of some (or all) of the passwords stored in the file by using publicly available tools and/or specialised tools on the Internet;
		users were able to use a password that did not comply the requirements for the creation of passwords set out in the Company’s IT security policy.
	
	
	The company did not assess, manage and could not manage the risks associated with the loss of confidentiality of personal data contained in this DB file (with appropriate organisational and technical security measures) as, according to the company, it was not aware of the existence of this DB file in the IT infrastructure it managed. This has led directly to the personal data breach and created the conditions for it to occur (sooner or later).


According to the SDPI, the confidentiality of personal data stored in the DB file would have been protected by the proper use of at least one of the following basic security measures: authenticated access to the DB file only for the staff members of the company; connecting to the storage only from the company’s internal computer network; storage of the DB file with encryption (entrusting the encryption keys only to the authorized staff members of the company); proper monitoring of information resources.

It should be noted that the company has taken the necessary measures to eliminate of, or mitigate, the effects of the PDB and has duly complied with the requirements of Article 33(3) of the GDPR.

 

DECISION

According to Article 83 (4) (a) of the GDPR, the administrative fine imposed on UAB Prime Leasing was based on the company’s total annual worldwide turnover for the preceding financial year (2020) and taking into account the circumstances of the case. The administrative fine of EUR 110,000 imposed under the decision of the SDPI for the established infringement of Article 32 (1) (a), (b), (d) of the GDPR, will achieve the objectives of the GDPR and will be dissuasive and proportionate. 

When deciding on the amount of the fine, the SDPI took into account the following aggravating and mitigating factors:


	Aggravating factor. The security of the DB file was not ensured since its creation resulted in a breach of confidentiality of personal data of a large number of data subjects (Article 83(2)(a) of the GDPR). Although the extent of the damage to the data subjects was not clear at the time of the proceedings, this does not mean that such damage will not occur in the future, especially since, due to the company’s own failure to ensure adequate data security, it is not clear how many persons have had unauthorised access to the DB file and to what extent the data have already been disseminated, but not yet exploited, and it is not yet clear where and to what extent they have been exploited, and such uses  are not yet known.   
	Aggravating factor. The confidentiality of a person’s unique identifier (personal identification number), which is not subject to change and which is prohibited from being made public (Article 3 (2) of the Law on Legal Protection of Personal Data) and according to which various types of information are interconnected in many registers and information systems of the Republic of Lithuania, has been breached due to inadequate data security. In addition, the totality of the personal data stored in the DB file in question directly and unambiguously identifies a specific natural person. It should be noted that these personal data were stored without any additional technical protection and were not encrypted (Article 83 (2) (g) of the GDPR).   
	The company did not apply a risk assessment to the personal data migration process and relied solely on the belief that its performance and the way it was performed was secure. The company, as data controller, had a duty to ensure the security of personal data not only during the data migration process but also during the further processing of the DB file. Such conduct of the company was considered as negligence (Article 83(2)(b) of the GDPR). The fact that the company's actions were found to be negligent rather than intentional provides a ground for mitigating the company’s liability. 


Circumstances taken into account but not considered as mitigating or aggravating factors:

 


	Following the occurrence of the PDB, the company took measures to eliminate or mitigate the PDB, or mitigate its consequences, and duly complied with the requirements of Article 33(3) of the GDPR following the occurrence of the PDB (Article 83(2)(c) of the GDPR). 
	The Company, as data controller, is directly responsible for the inadequate failure to comply with the requirements of Article 32 of the GDPR in respect of the referenced file (Article 83(2)(d) of the GDPR). 
	No sanctions were imposed on the company prior to the present case for infringement of Article 24 and/or Article 32 of the GDPR (Article 83(2)(e) of the GDPR). 
	The company cooperated with the SDPI during the inspection, however the cooperation was not related to the aim to remedy the infringement or to reduce the degree of its potential negative impact.  
	Although the SDPI initiated an investigation of the company on its own initiative based on information it received, the company informed the public about the PDB in respect of which the company’s security was examined. Moreover, the company informed the SDPI about the data breach within the time limits set out in Article 34 of the GDPR (Article 83(2)(h) of the GDPR). In view of the above, it is not considered that the company sought to conceal the personal data breach from the SDPI.  


The SDPI examined the case concerning the imposition of an administrative fine by oral procedure in a closed session and in the presence of representatives of the SDPI and of UAB Prime Leasing. Given that the personal data breach also concerned personal data of citizens of other Member States of the European Union, the decision taken in accordance with the GDPR was also agreed with the personal data protection supervisory authorities of those States. The supervisory authorities of the following countries considered themselves to be the concerned supervisory authorities: Ireland, Germany, Austria, Italy, Portugal, Estonia, Belgium, Denmark, the Netherlands, Spain, Latvia, Sweden, Luxembourg, France, Norway, Finland, Slovakia and Slovenia.

This decision may be appealed against to the Vilnius Regional Administrative Court within one month from the date of its service in a manner established by the Law on Administrative Proceedings of the Republic of Lithuania.
        

                                                    
                    Share
        
        
                            
                    
                
                                                    
                    
                
                                
    

    

    

                
        
        

        

    
    
    


            

            
                Back
                
                
            
        

        
            
                
                    
                        State Data Protection Inspectorate

Data about the Inspectorate is collected and stored in the Legal Person's Register. Registration code 188607912

L. Sapiegos str. 17, LT-10312 Vilnius, Phones: +370 5 271 2804 / 279 1445, Fax +370 5 261 9494, E-mail ada@ada.lt

Consultations by phone +370 5 212 7532
Monday–Thursday 9–11 AM and 1–3 PM

                        © Government of the Republic of Lithuania
                    

                    

                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                                                                        
                                        
                                    
                                
                                
                                    
                                        
                                    
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
                            
            
        
    

        
            
                
                    Date
                    2021 12 01
                
                                    
                        Rating
                        

    
            1
    

                    
                            
                                

        
                                                
                                    
                            

                                                
        The Personal Data Protection Supervisory Authority, the State Data Protection Inspectorate (SDPI), imposed an administrative fine of EUR 110,000 on UAB Prime Leasing, the operator of the short-term car rental platform CityBee, by its decision taken on 29 November 2021. The SDPI carried out an investigation on its own initiative following information that appeared in the public domain in February 2021 regarding a possible company’s customers personal data breach (PDB). The company was fined for breach of Article 32(1)(a), (b), (d) of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), which governs the obligation to ensure the security of processing of personal data.

ORIGIN OF THE BREACH

The investigation of UAB Prime Leasing has been launched on the initiative of the SDPI following information received that the personal data of the company’s customers, including personal identification numbers, had been made public. During the investigation, the company submitted a report to the Supervisory Authority on the PDB in the company’s IT infrastructure in accordance with the procedure established by legal acts. According to the company, it became aware of the breach from another company providing cyber-security services, which informed it that the CityBee’s customer data was published in CSV files on the website RaidForums.com. The investigation revealed that the publicly disposed data was obtained from an unprotected database backup BACPAC file (DB file) with a creation date of 27 February 2018. It turned out that the exact date of suspension of the external access to the said file was 16 February 2021 11:15 am. In the absence of any factual evidence to suggest that the said file was not publicly accessible during that period, it was concluded that the PDB lasted from 27 February 2018 to 16 February 2021.

Given the established ongoing nature of the PDB, and taking into account the start of the application of the GDPR, the Supervisory Authority assessed during the investigation the obligations of the company under the GDPR, both with regard to the PDB and the requirements for ensuring the security of personal data.  

MAIN RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATION

The investigation revealed the following:


	The date of creation of the DB file containing the personal data based on which the company’s customer personal data set in the CSV file was created and made public was 27 February 2018.
	The data of 110,302 CityBee users were disclosed and made public.
	433 users who had provided their residential address in other countries of the European Union and/or the European Economic Area were identified. 
	The following sensitive personal data were stored in plain text in a DB file: name, address, telephone number, e-mail address, personal identification number, driving licence number, type of payment card and the last four digits of the card number, the date of expiration of the payment card and the user identifier (token) in Braintree.
	The company failed to ensure adequate personal data management and control:
	
		did not appoint a person with appropriate competence to be responsible for security and risk management;
		did not separate the duties and responsibilities in the field of IT development and maintenance from the duties and responsibilities in the field of cyber security;
		did not ensure access to the DB file logs to record and store entries, and did not ensure that actions performed on DB files were recorded, monitored and evaluated;
		the DB file was stored unencrypted, so that a person with technical knowledge could get full access to the data contained in the file after downloading it. The personal identification numbers in the DB file were also stored in plain text and unprotected by hashing or encryption algorithms;
		the passwords in the DB file were encrypted with the weak and relatively insecure hashing algorithm SHA-1 . It was easy for persons with technical knowledge to find out the real (unmasked by means of hash) values of some (or all) of the passwords stored in the file by using publicly available tools and/or specialised tools on the Internet;
		users were able to use a password that did not comply the requirements for the creation of passwords set out in the Company’s IT security policy.
	
	
	The company did not assess, manage and could not manage the risks associated with the loss of confidentiality of personal data contained in this DB file (with appropriate organisational and technical security measures) as, according to the company, it was not aware of the existence of this DB file in the IT infrastructure it managed. This has led directly to the personal data breach and created the conditions for it to occur (sooner or later).


According to the SDPI, the confidentiality of personal data stored in the DB file would have been protected by the proper use of at least one of the following basic security measures: authenticated access to the DB file only for the staff members of the company; connecting to the storage only from the company’s internal computer network; storage of the DB file with encryption (entrusting the encryption keys only to the authorized staff members of the company); proper monitoring of information resources.

It should be noted that the company has taken the necessary measures to eliminate of, or mitigate, the effects of the PDB and has duly complied with the requirements of Article 33(3) of the GDPR.

 

DECISION

According to Article 83 (4) (a) of the GDPR, the administrative fine imposed on UAB Prime Leasing was based on the company’s total annual worldwide turnover for the preceding financial year (2020) and taking into account the circumstances of the case. The administrative fine of EUR 110,000 imposed under the decision of the SDPI for the established infringement of Article 32 (1) (a), (b), (d) of the GDPR, will achieve the objectives of the GDPR and will be dissuasive and proportionate. 

When deciding on the amount of the fine, the SDPI took into account the following aggravating and mitigating factors:


	Aggravating factor. The security of the DB file was not ensured since its creation resulted in a breach of confidentiality of personal data of a large number of data subjects (Article 83(2)(a) of the GDPR). Although the extent of the damage to the data subjects was not clear at the time of the proceedings, this does not mean that such damage will not occur in the future, especially since, due to the company’s own failure to ensure adequate data security, it is not clear how many persons have had unauthorised access to the DB file and to what extent the data have already been disseminated, but not yet exploited, and it is not yet clear where and to what extent they have been exploited, and such uses  are not yet known.   
	Aggravating factor. The confidentiality of a person’s unique identifier (personal identification number), which is not subject to change and which is prohibited from being made public (Article 3 (2) of the Law on Legal Protection of Personal Data) and according to which various types of information are interconnected in many registers and information systems of the Republic of Lithuania, has been breached due to inadequate data security. In addition, the totality of the personal data stored in the DB file in question directly and unambiguously identifies a specific natural person. It should be noted that these personal data were stored without any additional technical protection and were not encrypted (Article 83 (2) (g) of the GDPR).   
	The company did not apply a risk assessment to the personal data migration process and relied solely on the belief that its performance and the way it was performed was secure. The company, as data controller, had a duty to ensure the security of personal data not only during the data migration process but also during the further processing of the DB file. Such conduct of the company was considered as negligence (Article 83(2)(b) of the GDPR). The fact that the company's actions were found to be negligent rather than intentional provides a ground for mitigating the company’s liability. 


Circumstances taken into account but not considered as mitigating or aggravating factors:

 


	Following the occurrence of the PDB, the company took measures to eliminate or mitigate the PDB, or mitigate its consequences, and duly complied with the requirements of Article 33(3) of the GDPR following the occurrence of the PDB (Article 83(2)(c) of the GDPR). 
	The Company, as data controller, is directly responsible for the inadequate failure to comply with the requirements of Article 32 of the GDPR in respect of the referenced file (Article 83(2)(d) of the GDPR). 
	No sanctions were imposed on the company prior to the present case for infringement of Article 24 and/or Article 32 of the GDPR (Article 83(2)(e) of the GDPR). 
	The company cooperated with the SDPI during the inspection, however the cooperation was not related to the aim to remedy the infringement or to reduce the degree of its potential negative impact.  
	Although the SDPI initiated an investigation of the company on its own initiative based on information it received, the company informed the public about the PDB in respect of which the company’s security was examined. Moreover, the company informed the SDPI about the data breach within the time limits set out in Article 34 of the GDPR (Article 83(2)(h) of the GDPR). In view of the above, it is not considered that the company sought to conceal the personal data breach from the SDPI.  


The SDPI examined the case concerning the imposition of an administrative fine by oral procedure in a closed session and in the presence of representatives of the SDPI and of UAB Prime Leasing. Given that the personal data breach also concerned personal data of citizens of other Member States of the European Union, the decision taken in accordance with the GDPR was also agreed with the personal data protection supervisory authorities of those States. The supervisory authorities of the following countries considered themselves to be the concerned supervisory authorities: Ireland, Germany, Austria, Italy, Portugal, Estonia, Belgium, Denmark, the Netherlands, Spain, Latvia, Sweden, Luxembourg, France, Norway, Finland, Slovakia and Slovenia.

This decision may be appealed against to the Vilnius Regional Administrative Court within one month from the date of its service in a manner established by the Law on Administrative Proceedings of the Republic of Lithuania.
        

                                                    
                    Share
        
        
                            
                    
                
                                                    
                    
                
                                
    

    
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
      <sha1>32epwcpzmi27mjxeeoqwrqwmm042j2c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
